<!DOCTYPE appendix PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd">

<appendix id='ref-images'>
    <title>Reference: Images</title>

    <para>
        Poky has several standard images covering most people's standard needs. 
        Use the following command to list the supported images:
        <literallayout class='monospaced'>
     $ ls meta*/recipes*/images/*.bb
        </literallayout>
        Images are listed below along with details of what they contain:
    </para>

    <note>
        Building an image without GNU Public License Version 3 (GPLv3) components is 
        only supported for minimal and base images.
        Furthermore, if you are going to build an image using non-GPLv3 components,
        you must make the following changes in the <filename>local.conf</filename> file
        before using the BitBake command to build the minimal or base image:
        <literallayout class='monospaced'>
     1. Comment out the IMAGE_EXTRA_FEATURES line
     2. Set INCOMPATIBLE_LICENSE = "GPLv3"
        </literallayout>
    </note>

    <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    <emphasis>poky-image-minimal</emphasis> - A small image just capable 
                    of allowing a device to boot.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    <emphasis>poky-image-base</emphasis> - A console-only image that fully 
                    supports the target device hardware. 
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    <emphasis>poky-image-core</emphasis> - An X11 image with simple 
                    applications such as terminal, editor, and file manager.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    <emphasis>poky-image-sato</emphasis> - An X11 image with Sato theme and
                    Pimlico applications. 
                    The image also contains terminal, editor, and file manager.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    <emphasis>poky-image-sato-dev</emphasis> - An X11 image similar to 
                    poky-image-sato but
                    also includes a native toolchain and libraries needed to build applications 
                    on the device itself. The image also includes testing and profiling tools 
                    as well as debug symbols.  This image was formerly poky-image-sdk.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    <emphasis>poky-image-lsb</emphasis> - An image suitable for implementations 
                    that conform to Linux Standard Base (LSB).
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    <emphasis>meta-toolchain</emphasis> - This image generates a tarball 
                    that contains a stand-alone toolchain that can be used externally to Poky. 
                    The tarball is self-contained and unpacks to the 
                    <filename class="directory">/opt/poky</filename> directory. 
                    The tarball also contains a copy of QEMU and the scripts necessary to run 
                    poky QEMU images.
                </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para>
                    <emphasis>meta-toolchain-sdk</emphasis> - This image includes everything in 
                    meta-toolchain but also includes development headers and libraries
                    to form a complete standalone SDK. 
                    See the <link linkend='platdev-appdev-external-sdk'> 
                    External Development Using the Poky SDK</link> section for more information.
                </para>
            </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
</appendix>
<!-- 
vim: expandtab tw=80 ts=4 
-->
