<!DOCTYPE appendix PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd">

<appendix id='resources'>
<title>Contributing to Poky</title>

<section id='resources-intro'>
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>
        We're happy for people to experiment with Poky and there are a number of places to
        find help if you run into difficulties or find bugs. To find out how to download
        source code see the <link linkend='intro-getit'>Obtaining Poky</link> section of
        the Introduction.
    </para>
</section>

<section id='resources-bugtracker'>
    <title>Bugtracker</title>

    <para>
        Problems with Poky should be reported using the Bugzilla application at 
        <ulink url='http://bugzilla.yoctoproject.org/'></ulink>.
    </para>
</section>

<section id='resources-mailinglist'>
    <title>Mailing lists</title>

    <para>
        To subscribe to the mailing lists click on the following URLs and follow the instructions:
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>
            <ulink url='http://lists.yoctoproject.org/listinfo/yocto'></ulink> for a Yocto Discussions
            mailing list.
        </para></listitem>

        <listitem><para>
            <ulink url='http://lists.yoctoproject.org/listinfo/poky'></ulink> for a Poky Discussions 
            mailing list.
        </para></listitem>

        <listitem><para>
            <ulink url='http://lists.yoctoproject.org/listinfo/yocto-announce'></ulink> for a mailing list
            to receive offical Yocto Project announcements for developments and milestones.
        </para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

</section>

<section id='resources-irc'>
    <title>Internet Relay Chat (IRC)</title>

    <para>
        Two IRC channels on freenode are available for Yocto Project and Poky discussions:
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>
            #yocto
        </para></listitem>

        <listitem><para>
            #poky
        </para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    </para>
</section>

<section id='resources-links'>
    <title>Links</title>

    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>
            <ulink url='http://yoctoproject.org'>The Yocto Project website</ulink> - The home site
            for Yocto Project.
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
            <ulink url='http://pokylinux.org'>The Poky website</ulink> - The home site
            for Poky Linux.
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
            <ulink url='http://www.openedhand.com/'>OpenedHand</ulink> - The
            original company behind Poky.
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
            <ulink url='http://www.intel.com/'>Intel Corporation</ulink> - The
            company who acquired OpenedHand in 2008.
        </para></listitem>

        <listitem><para>
            <ulink url='http://www.openembedded.org/'>OpenEmbedded</ulink>
            - The upstream generic embedded distribution Poky derives
            from (and contributes to).
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
            <ulink url='http://developer.berlios.de/projects/bitbake/'>Bitbake</ulink>
            - The tool used to process Poky metadata.
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
            <ulink url='http://bitbake.berlios.de/manual/'>BitBake User
                Manual</ulink> - A comprehensive guide to the BitBake tool.
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
            <ulink url='http://pimlico-project.org/'>Pimlico</ulink> - A
            suite of lightweight Personal Information Management (PIM)
            applications designed primarily for handheld and mobile
            devices.
        </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>
            <ulink url='http://fabrice.bellard.free.fr/qemu/'>QEMU</ulink>
            - An open source machine emulator and virtualizer.
        </para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
</section>

<section id='resources-contributions'>
    <title>Contributions</title>

    <para>
        Contributions to Poky are very welcome. Patches should be sent to the Poky mailing list along with a Signed-off-by: line in the same style as the Linux kernel. Adding this line signifies the developer has agreed to the         Developer's Certificate of Origin 1.1:
    </para>

            <programlisting>
        Developer's Certificate of Origin 1.1

        By making a contribution to this project, I certify that:

        (a) The contribution was created in whole or in part by me and I
            have the right to submit it under the open source license
            indicated in the file; or

        (b) The contribution is based upon previous work that, to the best
            of my knowledge, is covered under an appropriate open source
            license and I have the right under that license to submit that
            work with modifications, whether created in whole or in part
            by me, under the same open source license (unless I am
            permitted to submit under a different license), as indicated
            in the file; or

        (c) The contribution was provided directly to me by some other
            person who certified (a), (b) or (c) and I have not modified
            it.

        (d) I understand and agree that this project and the contribution
            are public and that a record of the contribution (including all
            personal information I submit with it, including my sign-off) is
            maintained indefinitely and may be redistributed consistent with
            this project or the open source license(s) involved.
</programlisting>

    <para>
        A Poky contributions tree (poky-contrib, git://git.pokylinux.org/poky-contrib.git)
        exists for people to stage contributions in, for regular contributors.
        If people desire such access, please ask on the mailing list. Usually
        access will be given to anyone with a proven track record of good patches.
    </para>

</section>


</appendix>
<!-- 
vim: expandtab tw=80 ts=4 
-->
