<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd">

<chapter id='adt-eclipse'>

<title>Yocto Project Kernel Architecture and Use Manual</title>

<section id='eclipse'>
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>
        The Yocto Project presents the kernel as a fully patched, history-clean git
        repository. 
        The git tree represents the selected features, board support,
        and configurations extensively tested by Yocto Project. 
        The Yocto Project kernel allows the end user to leverage community
        best practices to seamlessly manage the development, build and debug cycles.
    </para>
    <para>
        This manual describes the Yocto Project kernel by providing information
        on its history, organization, benefits, and use.
        The manual consists of two sections:
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem><para>Concepts - Describes concepts behind the kernel.
                You will understand how the kernel is organized and why it is organized in 
                the way it is.  You will understand the benefits of the kernel's organization 
                and the mechanisms used to work with the kernel and how to apply it in your 
                design process.</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>Using the Kernel - Describes best practices and "how-to" information
                that lets you put the kernel to practical use.  Some examples are "How to Build a 
                Project Specific Tree", "How to Examine Changes in a Branch", and "Saving Kernel
                Modifications."</para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    <para>
        For more information on the kernel, see the following links:
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem><para><ulink url='http://ldn.linuxfoundation.org/book/1-a-guide-kernel-development-process'></ulink></para></listitem>
            <listitem><para><ulink url='http://userweb.kernel.org/~akpm/stuff/tpp.txt'></ulink></para></listitem>
            <listitem><para><ulink url='http://git.kernel.org/?p=linux/kernel/git/torvalds/linux-2.6.git;a=blob_plain;f=Documentation/HOWTO;hb=HEAD'></ulink></para></listitem> 
        </itemizedlist>
        <para> 
        You can find more information on Yocto Project by visiting the website at
        <ulink url='http://www.yoctoproject.org'></ulink>.
        </para>
    </para>
</section>







</chapter>
<!--
vim: expandtab tw=80 ts=4
-->
